Guide to the Al cantío de un gallo Radio Program Audio Recordings
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Tape 443, Circa 1994-1998; 1 (Box 443)
  Side A: Un programa de Descubriendo la verdad en que los interlocutores hablan del turismo en Cuba. Dan varias estadísticas sobre el turismo; se ve que entre 1988 y 1992 ha habido una subida de un 20 por ciento en el número de turistas. Sin embargo, Cuba todavía recibe menos visitantes que los demás países caribeños por falta de vuelos comerciales a la isla. Esto es debido a los bajos niveles de infraestructura. Luego hablan del uso del dólar en la isla, la inversión extranjera en la economía cubana, la relación entre los turistas y los ciudadanos, y los posibles beneficios del turismo para el pueblo cubano. También dicen que el Caribe se volvió un destino de viaje popular gracias a la atención que llamó la Revolución cubana.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 444, Circa 1994-1998; 1 (Box 444)
  Side A: The speakers discuss the subject of reforms in Cuba. They mention that there is no real change because the Cuban leaders have no interest in losing their position of privilege. They say that ironically, wealth is poorly distributed in Cuba after a revolution was staged to better distribute capital, but there is no incentive to seek solutions. They talk about Fidel as an individual of immense selfishness who has caused the Cuban people's current situation by allying himself with the losers of the Cold War. They mention that they have to eliminate Fidel in order to help the Cuban people move forward.
  Side B: The speakers discuss why the exile community is so fervently concerned with Cuba. They mention that Cuba is not Cuba without those that are missing, especially now that their absence is so strongly felt. They lament the better days of Cuba before the revolution, and discuss whether the youth in Cuba has a concept of freedom and free elections. They advocate for the sharing of leadership among different people, and discuss the negative connotations attributed to the concept of "revolution" due to Castro's actions in power.
  Side A: Los locutores discuten el tema de las reformas en Cuba. Menciona que no hay cambio verdadero porque los líderes cubanos no tienen interés en perder su privilegio actual. Dicen que las riquezas de Cuba están mal distribuidas ahora, lo que es irónico considerando que la revolución era para distribuir mejor el dinero. No existe ningún incentivo para buscar soluciones. Hablan de Fidel como un individuo de inmenso egoísmo que ha provocado la presente situación del pueblo cubano por haberse aliado con los perdedores de la Guerra Fría. Mencionan que tienen que eliminar a Fidel para llevar adelante al pueblo cubano en el futuro.
  Side B: Los locutores discuten las razones por las que los exiliados se preocupan por Cuba de una manera tan ferviente. Mencionan que Cuba no es Cuba sin los que faltan, sobre todo ahora que se siente su ausencia. Lamentan la pérdida de una época mejor en Cuba antes de la revolución. Discuten si la juventud en Cuba tiene un concepto de la libertad y las elecciones libres. Abogan por el compartimiento del liderazgo entre diferentes personas, y hablan de las connotaciones negativas que ha cobrado el concepto de "revolución" por culpa de las acciones de Castro mientras ha estado en el poder.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 445, Circa 1994-1998; 1 (Box 445)
  Side A: The host contacts journalists from Cuba. Journalist Omar Rodríguez talks about how the government seeks support for the new Mambises, or guerrilla fighters. They talk about the project Carta de Cuba, a magazine in its third publication that serves to spread the coverage of independent journalists throughout Cuba. Then, they talk about an explosion at the Cohíba Hotel and a fire in Havana that was said to be accidental, although the speakers suggest that the fire's cause is still unknown due to lack of information.
  Side B: The host contacts journalists on the island to learn the latest news from there. Journalist Lázaro Lazo reports from Cuba on the immigration of farmers to the capital, and the government's policy of deporting many of them to the provinces. Then, Mercedes Moreno follows with a report on the Democratic Solidarity Party leader, Hector Palacio Ruiz, who has been arrested and has not received humane treatment as a prisoner. Another report mentions that the Cuban sugar cane harvest will not reach the desired level, although the regime is trying to cover up the numbers. Finally, the speakers return to the topic of the explosion at the Hotel Cohíba and wonder if it was an attack of resistance against the regime or just an accident.
  Side A: El locutor contacta a periodistas reportando desde Cuba. El periodista Omar Rodríguez habla sobre la manera en que el gobierno busca apoyo para su política de los nuevos mambises, o guerrilleros. Hablan sobre el proyecto de Carta de Cuba, revista en su tercera publicación que sirve para divulgar los reportajes de los periodistas independientes por toda Cuba. Luego, hablan sobre una explosión en el Hotel Cohíba y un incendio en La Habana que supuestamente fue un accidente, aunque los interlocutores señalan que realmente no se sabe el origen del incendio por la falta de información.
  Side B: El locutor contacta a periodistas en la isla para estar al día con las noticias desde Cuba. El periodista Lázaro Lazo reporta desde Cuba sobre la inmigración de campesinos hacia la capital y la deportación de gran cantidad de ellos a las provincias por parte del gobierno. Luego, Mercedes Moreno sigue con un reportaje sobre el líder del partido Solidaridad Democrática, Héctor Palacio Ruiz, quien ha sido detenido y no ha recibido el nivel de tratamiento debido a cualquier prisionero. Otro reportaje menciona que la zafra cubana no va a llegar al nivel deseado, aunque el gobierno intenta ocultar las cifras. Al final, retoman el tema de la explosión del Hotel Cohíba, preguntándose si fue un atentado de la resistencia contra el régimen o un accidente.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 446, Circa 1994-1998; 1 (Box 446)
  Side A: This special edition of the program is called the Musical parade and represents the rhythm of the free world. It is a broadcast of what the speakers call "music of the free world," which represents a range of Cuban artists living in exile and artists from before the revolution. Most of the songs are ballads and romances.
  Side B: Melero and Franqui celebrate the 150th anniversary of the birth of José Martí with a discussion of his ideas. They believe that Martí's thought is opposed to that of Castro, who has installed himself as a caudillo in Cuba, ruling over a monoculture based on the sugar trade. Martí, in contrast, believed in a republican government, free press and universal education. The speakers indicate that Martí was not against the US, although Castro has adopted him as part of his anti-American rhetoric. The speakers caution against confusing the wealth and investment that the United States can provide with fears of annexation and neocolonialism.
  Side A: Esta edición especial del programa se llama el Desfile musical, que representa el ritmo del mundo libre. Transmiten lo que llaman "música del mundo libre" que representa una gama de artistas cubanos en el exilio y artistas de la época antes de la revolución. La mayor parte de las canciones son baladas y romances.
  Side B: Melero y Franqui celebran el aniversario de 150 años después del nacimiento de José Martí con un discurso sobre sus ideas. Creen que el pensamiento de Martí está en oposición al de Fidel Castro, quien se ha instalado como caudillo en Cuba, rigiendo una monocultura basada en el azúcar. Martí, en cambio, creía en el gobierno republicano, la prensa libre y la educación universal. Señalan que Martí no era en contra de los Estados Unidos, aunque Castro lo haya adoptado como parte de su retórica antiamericana. Advierten contra confundir la riqueza e inversiones de los Estados Unidos con el miedo a la anexión y al neocolonialismo.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 447, Circa 1994-1998; 1 (Box 447)
  Side A: Melero and Franqui discuss the weakness of the Castro regime, which has been maintaining its power by means of an apparatus of repression. They say that the exports of sugar, nickel and medicine are used by the regime keep its repressive apparatus; however, in recent years this economic balance is beginning to fail with regard to sugar and nickel. Since Cuba trades nickel resources for oil with Russia, the news of the decline of the nickel industry will likely result in more blackouts for the Cuban people. The Cuban economy will reach a full paralysis with the decline of the two most powerful industries on the island. The speakers hope this will result in the fall of the Castro regime.
  Side B: Franqui and Melero begin by discussing the particular connection between the Dominican Republic and Cuba. They lament the fact that one Dominican university gave an honorary degree to Fidel Castro while another criticized his treatment of prisoners on the island. They continue with a report on "Cuba on the edge of the abyss," which exposes the crisis toward which the island is approaching. They discuss how the predictions made years ago are becoming a reality as Cuba's situation becomes apocalyptic. To conclude, they discuss the progress made by the Czech Republic, where Vaclav Havel was elected president after being imprisoned for advocating the movement against the Communists.
  Side A: Melero y Franqui discuten la debilidad del régimen castrista que se mantiene en el poder por medio de un aparato de represión. Dicen que la exportación del azúcar, el níquel y las medicinas ayuda a sostener este aparato; sin embargo, en los últimos años este equilibrio económico empieza a fallar con respecto al azúcar y al níquel. Dado que Cuba cambia sus recursos de níquel por petróleo con Rusia, el declive de la industria de níquel va a resultar en más apagones para el pueblo cubano. La economía cubana va a llegar a una parálisis total con la caída de las dos industrias más poderosas en la isla. Los interlocutores esperan que esta crisis lleve a la caída del régimen castrista.
  Side B: Franqui y Melero empiezan por hablar del vínculo singular entre Santo Domingo y Cuba. Lamentan que una universidad dominicana le haya dado un título honorario a Castro al mismo tiempo que otra universidad protesta su tratamiento de los prisioneros en la isla. Continúan con un reportaje acerca de "Cuba al borde del abismo", que expone la crisis a la cual se está aproximando la isla. Comentan que las realidades proyectadas hace años están realizándose ahora con la llegada de Cuba a una situación apocalíptica. Para terminar, hablan del progreso en la República Checa, donde Václav Havel fue elegido presidente después de estar encarcelado por defender el movimiento contra los comunistas.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 448, Circa 1994-1998; 1 (Box 448)
  Side A: This recording only has Melero counting votes for some function. The rest of the tape is blank and is filled with background noise.
  Side B: [Duplicate of Tape 446, Side B.]
  Side A: En esta grabación sólo se escucha a Melero contando votos para alguna función. El resto de la cinta está en blanco y está lleno de ruido de fondo.
  Side B: [Copia de Tape 446, Side B.]
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 449, Circa 1994-1998; 1 (Box 449)
  Side A: Melero and Franqui discuss the issue of Cuba's moral, religious, economic and overall decline. They mention how Castro uses terror tactics and force to keep himself in power. They hope that during the centennial of independence Cuba can return to a freedom movement in the same way that the attack on Moncada which launched the Cuban Revolution occurred during the centennial of the birth of José Martí. They discuss how Fidel Castro's poor choice in taking the side of the Soviet Union will have a major impact on Cuba and continue its decline. The speakers blame Castro and his regime for not investing the resources that the Soviet Union gave Cuba and mismanaging funds. They discuss how communism has produced misery in Cuba and continues to drag the country down after the fall of its country of origin, the Soviet Union.
  Side B: Melero and Franqui continue discussing possible solutions to Cuba's problems. According to them, Cuba has four forces at work: the irreversible decline of the island, the forces attempting to mitigate that decline, those fleeing the island and the resistance on the island that undermines the status quo. They discuss how Castro will eventually fall when his repression tactics fail. They discuss the psychology of Castro and his obsession with power that has continued to move him to lead the country. Franqui mentions that the escape of many people and the impetus to rebel have started to end the regime's power. Melero asserts that he has never had faith in Castro's generals, because they were chosen for their ability to be controlled, and believes that they are not capable of defending communism or overthrowing the current system.
  Side A: Melero y Franqui discuten la tesis de la caída moral, religiosa, económica y global de Cuba. Mencionan la manera en que la táctica castrista de terror emplea la fuerza para mantener a Castro en el poder. Esperan que en el centenario de la independencia, Cuba pueda regresar a un movimiento de libertad de la misma manera que el ataque en Moncada ocurrió durante el centenario del nacimiento de Martí. Discuten la mala decisión de Castro de tomar el lado de la Unión Soviética y las repercusiones con las que tendrá que lidiar. Los interlocutores ponen la culpa de la situación cubana en Castro por no haber invertido los recursos que le dio la Unión Soviética y la mala administración de los fondos a través de su régimen. Según ellos, el comunismo ha producido la miseria en Cuba y seguirá hundiendo al país ahora que ha caído su país de origen, la Unión Soviética.
  Side B: Melero y Franqui siguen hablando de posibles soluciones a los problemas de Cuba. Según ellos, Cuba tiene cuatro fuerzas en acción ahora: la caída irreversible, la fuerza de detener esta caída, la fuerza de huir y la fuerza de la resistencia en la isla. Creen que Castro caerá con su régimen cuando la represión deje de funcionar. Discuten la psicología de Castro y su obsesión con el poder que lo ha impulsado a mantenerse en el poder. Según Franqui, la fuga de la gente y la rebelión han comenzado a debilitar el poder del régimen. Melero asevera que nunca ha tenido fe en el liderazgo de los generales del régimen porque Castro los escogió por lo fácil que eran de controlar, y cree que no son capaces ni de defender el comunismo ni de derribar el sistema actual.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 450, Circa 1994-1998; 1 (Box 450)
  Side A: Melero and Franqui talk about business on the island and how luxury items are only accessible to tourists and members of the Castro regime. They mention how Castro has devastated Cuba by preventing the use of the US dollar among the Cuban people while tourists and Castro can buy luxury products using other currencies. They criticize the way that Castro did not invest the billions of dollars the communist world donated to Cuba, but instead spent it all on the wars in Angola. They contrast the abject poverty of the Cuban people with the luxurious lives of Castro's lackeys and tourists. They mention that the Cuban people suffer from the embargo imposed by Castro, while the American embargo only limits the regime from buying more luxury items.
  Side B: Melero and Franqui discuss an article by Luis Aguilar León on Cuban humor and how Fidel Castro has not been able to eliminate it. The article describes the future in 2009, the fiftieth anniversary of the Cuban Revolution. It describes a future in which Cuba has become an archaic country that is afraid of change. It is a description of a future dystopia in which Cubans fear the return of the exiles' children and grandchildren who may take all they have. They discuss the irony in this article, since the Cubans in this dystopian future have been degraded to such primitivism that the exiles living in prosperity have no incentive to take anything from them. Finally, they discuss how Cuban exiles have changed Miami, Chicago, San Juan and New York for the better and can provide the same support for their Cuban brothers to transform Havana into a dynamic city once again.
  Side A: Melero y Franqui hablan sobre los negocios en la isla y la manera en que sólo existen las cosas lujosas para los turistas y los miembros del régimen. Mencionan cómo Castro ha devastado la isla, previniendo el uso del dólar americano entre los cubanos mismos mientras que los turistas y Castro tienen acceso a todos los productos de lujo. Reprochan el hecho de que Castro no haya invertido los billones de dólares que el mundo comunista donó a Cuba, sino que lo gastó todo en las guerras en Angola. Discuten la miseria absoluta en que vive el pueblo cubano, en contraste con el alto estándar de vida de Castro y los turistas. Afirman que el pueblo sufre por el embargo castrista en vez del embargo norteamericano que sólo limita la compra de productos de lujo por el régimen.
  Side B: Melero y Franqui discuten un artículo de Luis Aguilar León sobre el humor cubano que Fidel Castro no ha podido reprimir. El artículo describe el futuro en el 2009, el quincuagésimo aniversario de la Revolución Cubana. Se describe un futuro en que Cuba ha llegado a ser un país arcaico que tiene miedo al cambio. Es una descripción de una futura distopía en que los cubanos temen que los hijos y nietos de los exiliados regresen para tomar todo lo que tienen. Discuten la ironía de este artículo, dado que los cubanos han llegado a una situación tan primitiva en este futuro que los exiliados viviendo en la prosperidad no tendrán ningún motivo para reapropiarse de Cuba. Al final, discuten la manera en que los exiliados cubanos han mejorado las ciudades de Miami, Chicago, San Juan y Nueva York y pueden aportar el mismo apoyo a sus hermanos cubanos para transformar a La Habana en una ciudad dinámica.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 451, Circa 1994-1998; 1 (Box 451)
  Side A: Discussion of the embargo. Franqui believes that the US embargo against Cuba is a lie, a product of Castro's propaganda. He says that there are more than fifty international capitalist companies in Cuba. He lists several of the largest of these companies, their country of origen, and the products they sell. He mentions Benetton, Rolex, Jaguar, and other companies that deal with trucks, cosmetics, pharmaceuticals, and hotels. He says that the tourists, who are the ones that buy from these companies, are robbing the country. Melero calls it a kind of "touristic apartheid." Franqui says the US embargo does not affect the people of Cuba, but rather it affects Castro, since he is the only one that buys these products, especially Rolex watches. Also, the embargo does not affect the citizens because Cuba could buy the same products from other countries besides the US, such as petroleum from Ecuador, if Cuba had its own internal production.
  Side B: The fear of change. Melero reads an article, "El miedo a todos los miedos" ("The Fear of All Fears"), by Dr. Luis Aguilar León, a professor of the Universidad del Aire ("University of the Air"). Franqui discusses some of the important points of the article: the use of humor and the absurdity of fearing change in Cuba. Melero quotes Dr. Dora Rivas, who has said, "The country is dying between our hands." Franqui says that those that are afraid of change are the ones who are tied to the regime. Melero compares Miama with Havana, and says that the exiled Cubans have made Miami more Cuban than Havana. Franqui says that those in exile are Cubans who are free and that they help Cuba by bringing their Cuban identity to North American cities. The reign of Castro, according to Franqui, is a reign of hunger and terror that causes a fear of change, but change is the only solution.
  Side A: El embargo americano. Franqui plantea que el embargo de los EEUU contra Cuba es una mentira, un producto de la propaganda por parte de Castro. Dice que hay más de cincuenta compañías capitalistas internacionales que venden en Cuba. Enumera unas de las más grandes de estas compañías, su país de origen, y sus productos. Menciona Benetton, Rolex, Jaguar, y otras compañías de camiones, cosméticos, farmacéuticos, y hoteles. Dice que los turistas, que son los que pueden comprar de estas compañías, roban al país. Melero dice que una suerte de "apartheid turístico." Franqui dice que el embargo americano no afecta al pueblo cubano, sino a Castro, ya que él es el único que compra esos productos, sobre todo los relojes Rolex. Además el embargo americano no afecta al pueblo cubano porque Cuba podría comprar los mismos productos de otros países que no sean los EEUU, como el petróleo que se puede comprar de Ecuador, si Cuba tuviera una producción interna.
  Side B: El miedo al cambio. Melero lee un artículo, "El miedo a todos los miedos" de Dr. Luis Aguilar León, profesor de la Universidad del Aire. Franqui comenta unos puntos importantes del artículo: el uso de humor y el absurdo miedo al cambio en Cuba. Melero cita a Dra. Dora Rivas, quien ha dicho, "El país se nos muere entre las manos." Franqui dice que los que tienen miedo al cambio son los que están comprometidos al régimen. Melero habla de una comparación entre Miami y La Habana, y dice que los exiliados han hecho a Miami más cubana que La Habana. Franqui dice que los exiliados son los cubanos libres y que ayudan a Cuba por trasladar la identidad cubana a las ciudades norteamericanas. El reino de Castro, según Franqui, es uno de hambre y terror que provoca el miedo al cambio, pero el cambio es la única solución.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 452, 1994 August 29; 1 (Box 452)
  Side A: The Flight. Melero and Franqui discuss the flight of Cuban citizens out of Cuba, which they consider to be the centrifugal force of the rebellion in the country. Franqui says that the cause of the flight is the pressure from Castro and his barbaric behavior. The upcoming centennial of the death of José Martí should jumpstart the movement for liberty in Cuba. He compares the situation today to the catastrophe in 1980, when a thousand Cubans took over the Peruvian Embassy in Havana, asking for asylum. He speaks about Castro's attempts to terrorize Americans and about President Clinton's reaction to Castro. Franqui compares the present situation in Cuba with the military coup of Batista in 1952.
  Side B: The Forces of the Revolution. Melero lists four forces that direct the rebellion in Cuba: the fall of Castro; his attempts to avoid said defeat; the flee (centrifugal force); and the changes within the country (centripetal force). Franqui refers to the arrival of Castro in 1953, saying that young people were the protagonists in that rebellion, and it is they who must be the protagonists again. Franqui hopes that the upcoming centennial of the death of José Martí will galvanize the youth to get organized and fight. Melero says that the youth have education not thanks to Castro, but to Cuba. Castro, on the contrary, hinders their freedom of thought. If they plan to have children, says Melero, they must make Cuba free for them. He remembers the date of 1895 and the debate between Martí, Antonio Maceo y Grajales, and Máximo Gómez regarding the independence of Cuba.